Guide to the Johnson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Johnson family papers
1631-2010
1631-1918
MS 305
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
30.02
(45 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, papers, volumes, deeds, and other material documenting several generations of the Johnson family of Connecticut and New York. Samuel Johnson (1696-1772), William Samuel Johnson (1727-1819), William Samuel Johnson (1795-1883), and Samuel William Johnson (1828-1895) are prominent figures in the papers. The correspondence of William Livingston (1723-1790) and Noah Welles (1718-1776) is also arranged in the papers. In addition to extensive correspondence between Johnson family members, the papers contain material relating to Connecticut and New York politics in the colonial and Revolutionary War periods, and religion, land development, and Indian affairs in the nineteenth century. Additions to the papers include family correspondence, sketchbooks of Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson, a diary and account books of Sarah Dwight Woolsey Johnson, photographs by Robert Bayard Severy; Livington family genealogy, by Margaret S. Rutgers; multi-generational account book, and photographs of eighteenth-century documents related to William Samuel Johnson.
Johnson family
Existence and Location of Copies
The correspondence of William Livingston to Noah Welles is also available on microfilm (340 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM14.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Geraldine, Ethel, and Lawrence J. Carmalt, 1984. Gift of Robert Bayard Severy, 2003-2006. Gift of Donald Severy, Robert Bayard Severy, and Arabella Olander, 2008, 2009 and 2012.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and eight additions: Series I. Correspondence and Business Papers, 1664-1886. Series II. Volumes, 1759-1900. Series III. Folios, 1644-1843.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, papers, volumes, deeds, and other material documenting several generations of the Johnson family of Connecticut and New York. Samuel Johnson (1696-1772), William Samuel Johnson (1727-1819), William Samuel Johnson (1795-1883), and Samuel William Johnson (1828-1895) are prominent figures in the papers. The correspondence of William Livingston (1723-1790) and Noah Welles (1718-1776) is also arranged in the papers. In addition to extensive correspondence between Johnson family members, the papers contain material relating to Connecticut and New York politics in the colonial and Revolutionary War periods, and religion, land development, and Indian affairs in the nineteenth century. Additions to the papers include family correspondence, sketchbooks of Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson, a diary and account books of Sarah Dwight Woolsey Johnson, photographs of New Haven, Yale University, and other Connecticut towns by Robert Bayard Severy; Livington family genealogy, by Margaret S. Rutgers; multi-generational account book, and photographs of eighteenth-century documents related to William Samuel Johnson. The originals of these documents, all of which are in the public domain, were donated to Columbia University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Johnson, Samuel (1696-1772): Connecticut clergyman, and educator, first and founding president of the King's (later Columbia) College. Born in Guilford, Connecticut, entered Yale College in 1710. Graduated in 1714. Ordained a minister in 1720 in the Congregational church, beginning his parish work in West Haven, Connecticut. Resigned from that position in 1723, and was ordained a minister of the Episcopal Church during the sojourn in Great Britain, where he was awarded the degree of MA from both Oxford and Cambridge. Following his return, became the rector of the church in Stratford, Connecticut. During the residence at Stratford, Johnson wrote several treatises, published by Benjamin Franklin and used as textbooks at the University of Pennsylvania. In 1743 he was awarded the degree of D. D. from Oxford. In 1754 moved to New York City at the solicitation of the trustees of the new King's College to become the president of the school. Resigned in 1763, returning to his old parish as rector in 1764. Died at Stratford, Connecticut.
Johnson, William Samuel (1727-1819): Connecticut statesman, attorney, judge and educator. First president of the Columbia College (now University) in New York, New York. Born in Stratford, Connecticut, of Samuel Johnson and his mother, daughter of Col. Richard Floyd. Graduated from Yale with the A.B. in 1744 at the age of seventeen. Following his graduation, pursued theological studies as a "scholar of the house" under Dean Berkeley, after which decided to become a lawyer, enrolling in the course of studies for MA degree at Harvard College on May 30, 1747. He attained a high standing in his profession as he was always secured as counsel in both religious controversies and juridical disputes of the Connecticut colony, for which he was called "the father of the bar in Connecticut."
Representative to Connecticut's general assembly from Stratford (elected in 1761, 1765, and 1772), and from the state of Connecticut to the Stamp Act Congress in 1765. Selected as a special envoy to Great Britain in 1766 representing the colony's land title claims. In 1772, one of the judges of the superior court of Connecticut. A delegate at the Continental congress, and leader of the Connecticut delegation to the Constitutional Convention of 1787. First president of Columbia (former King's) College (1792-1800).
Johnson, William Samuel (1795-1883) and Samuel William Johnson (1828-1895), father and son, were land office proprietors in Cattaraugus, New York.
Business; Families; Indians of North America; Land companies -- New York (State) -- Cattaraugus County; Law; Seneca Indians; Stockbridge Indians; Connecticut -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Connecticut -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Europe; New York (State); New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Southern States; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Diaries; Clergy; College presidents; Berkeley, George; Carmalt, Laura Woolsey Johnson, 1837-1924; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789; Devereux, George Pollock, 1796-; Devereux, Sarah Edwards Johnson, 1797-1867; Hudson, Susan Edwards Johnson, 1825-1913; Johnson, Ann Francis, 1792-; Johnson, Charles Frederick, 1836-1931; Johnson, Edwards, 1804-1873; Johnson, Katharine Livingston Bayard, 1845-1906; Johnson, Laura Woolsey, 1800-1880; Johnson, Robert Charles, 1807-1886; Johnson, Samuel William, 1761-1846; Johnson, Samuel William, 1828-1895; Johnson, Samuel, 1696-1772; Johnson, Susan Edwards, 1771-1856; Johnson, William Samuel, 1727-1819; Johnson, William Samuel, 1795-1883; Johnson, Woolsey, 1842-1887; Kneeland, Ebenezer, 1777-; Livingston, William, 1723-1790; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Verplank, Elizabeth Johnson, 1763-1789; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Welles, Noah, 1718-1776; Columbia University; L.L. Johnson Land Company; Johnson family
- Correspondence and Business Papers, 1664-1886; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in three sections: Chronological, Deeds, and Select. Chronological and Deeds are arranged in chronological order.
  Series I contains the personal letters, financial papers, and other materials of several Johnson family members and unrelated individuals. Among the earliest Johnson family letters are those of Robert Charles Johnson (1766-1806), which include information on Florida property ventures (circa 1780-1810). Family members frequently maintained a regular and lengthy correspondence with their relatives. William Samuel Johnson (1795-1883) began writing his sister Ann while at Yale College in 1812, and the pair continued to exchange letters for many years. Similarly, William Samuel Johnson corresponded with his father, Samuel William Johnson (1761-1846) from the 1820s through 1846. Other prominent figures in the network of family correspondents include: Laura Woolsey Johnson, wife of William Samuel Johnson, and Samuel Johnson (1696-1772) and William Samuel Johnson (1727-1819). Material in the Chronological section documents the personal thoughts and activities of family members from the 1760s through the 1880s, and also includes much information on the business interests of individuals.
  Deeds contain several hundred deeds relating to Johnson family members in Connecticut and elsewhere from 1664-1776.
  Select files consist of the correspondence of Samuel Johnson and George Berkeley, 1756-1767, and other papers, 1733-1737. The correpondence of William Livingston (1723-1790) and Noah Welles (1718-1776) is also arranged in this section. Both men were in the Yale College Class of 1741. Livingston served as the first governor of New Jersey and Welles was a Congregational Church minister in Stanford, Connecticut. In letters written from 1742-1768 Livingston addresses Welles as a friend and discusses many events in his personal and professional life.
  - Chronological
    - 1785 July-1822 December (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
    - 1823 January-1827 August (Box 2, Folder 12-19)
    - 1827 September-1831 December (Box 3, Folder 20-27)
    - 1832 January 18-1839 August 21 (Box 4, Folder 28-37)
    - 1839 October-1844 April 30 (Box 5, Folder 38-48)
    - 1844 May 1-1847 January 20 (Box 6, Folder 49-59)
    - 1847 August 3-1849 September 22 (Box 7, Folder 60-69)
    - 1849 October 1-1852 December 31 (Box 8, Folder 70-78)
    - 1853 February 9-1855 May 31 (Box 9, Folder 79-88)
    - 1855 June 1-1856 December 31 (Box 10, Folder 89-98)
    - 1857 January-1858 May 29 (Box 11, Folder 99-106)
    - 1858 June 4-1860 June (Box 12, Folder 107-115)
    - 1860 July-1864 February (Box 13, Folder 116-125)
    - 1864 March-1867 May (Box 14, Folder 126-137)
    - 1867 June-1886, undated (Box 15, Folder 138-150)
    - Undated (Box 16, Folder 151-162)
  - Deeds, 1664-1776 (Box 17, Folder 163-168)
  - Select
    - Johnson, Samuel to Berkeley, George, 1733-1789 (Box 18, Folder 169-177)
    - Livingston, William to Welles, Noah, 1742-1768 (Box 19, Folder 178-185)
- Volumes, 1759-1900; Series II
  This series is arranged in five sections: Johnson, William Samuel; Johnson, Laura Woolsey; Johnson, Robert Charles; Johnson, Susan Edwards; and Johnson family. Each section is arranged alphabetically by record type. The series contains account books, daybooks, journals, letterbooks, and other items for Johnson family members. The bulk of these items are arranged under the name "Johnson, William Samuel" although certain volumes, such as legal notebooks dated 1759 are generally considered those of one William Samuel Johnson (1727-1819), and other material is more likely related to a later William Samuel Johnson (1795-1883). Volumes of Laura Woolsey Johnson, Robert Charles Johnson, Susan Edward Johnson, and other family members are also arranged in this series.
  - Johnson, William Samuel
    - Account book, 1823-1833 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Account book, 1823-1859 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Cost book, legal, 1821-1826 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Daybook, 1825-1833 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Journal, 1799-1800 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Ledger, 1821-1842 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Letterbook, 1851-1855 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Letterbook, 1829-1837 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Notebook, legal, 1759 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Notebook, legal, 1759 (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Paper: Indian affairs, 1830-1840 (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Record book: legal, 1806-1822 (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Record book: legal, 1830-1832 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Johnson, Laura Woolsey: diary and notes, 1861-1900 (Box 24, Folder 14)
  - Johnson, Robert Charles: record book, legal, 1790 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  - Johnson, Susan Edward: journal, 1801-1802 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  - Johnson family
    - Legal papers, undated (Box 24, Folder 17-18)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 24, Folder 19)
- Folios, 1644-1843; Series III
  Series III contains many large documents, including deeds, indentures, maps, newspapers, and other papers relating to the Johnson family.
  - Deeds, indentures, maps, and papers, 1644-1843 (Box 26, Folder 25, Folder 27, Folder 29)
  - Newspapers, brochure, flyers, 1814-1828, 1844-1846 (Folder 28)
- Additional materials, 1631-1918; Accession 2003-M-084
  The addition is mostly comprised of correspondence, but includes financial documents, photographs, and books. Approximately ninety percent of the correspondence is letters between Katharine L. Bayard Johnson of Paris, France, and her uncle, William Johnson, and her aunt, Anna Bellamy Johnson of Dorchester, Massachusetts. The letters document family and personal matters, such as health; relationships; and travels in Spain, France, Switzerland, Germany, Austria, Italy and England; as well as Katharine's activities as a freelance artist in Paris. There are also Katharine's notes on Parisian theaters, novelists, salons, and cultural life in general. There are notes by Anna Bellamy on Northeastern United States cultural life. A good portion of the correspondence is devoted to business matters, including management of the Johnson estate, family investments, Katharine's inheritance, and exhibition and sales of her paintings and artwork. [Correspondence between Katharine L. Bayard Johnson and her aunt Anna Bellamy Johnson for the years 1897-1900 is microfilmed and available at the Smithsonian Archives of American Art.]
  - Correspondence
    - 1789 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1792-1793 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1793-1798, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1804-1864 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1866-1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1870, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1873 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - 1874 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    - 1875 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - 1876-1886, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-25)
    - 1887-1893 (Box 3, Folder 26-32)
      General
      1889 correspondence includes letter regarding the Woolsey funeral at Yale.
    - 1894-1902, undated (Box 4, Folder 33-42)
    - 1903-1905, undated (Box 5, Folder 43-47)
      Includes fragments.
  - Biographical and genealogical, Undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Financial, 1872-1918 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous, 1873-1883 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Books
    - Cicero, M. T. Epistolae Selectae, London, 1657 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - [Nicolle, M.?] Epigrammatum Delectus ex omnibus tum veteribus, tum recentioribus Poetis, London, 1683 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Pareus, Daniel. Titi Lucretii Cari Philosophi et Poetae antiquissimi De Rerum Natura Libri Sex [also includes Lucretius' Vita, Testimonia, and excerpts from Scipion Capicio's De Principiis Rerum; and from Aonius Palearis' De Animorum Immortalitate Liber Primus ], Frankfurt, 1631 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Milton, John. Paradise Lost, London, 1751 (Box 7, Folder 55)
- Additional materials, 1788-1907; Accession 2004-M-091
  The addition contains mostly personal papers, correspondence, and photographs of various members and relatives of the Johnson family. The materials are arranged in alphabetical order by family member's last name.
  Correspondence comprises the majority of the material in the folders, followed by travel notes and diaries (Charles Frederick and Robert Charles Johnson), and estate management documents (George Hoadley, William Samuel Johnson, Augustus Hillhouse). In addition, almost every folder contains obituary clippings providing biographical information on the individual. One folder at the end of the inventory contains photocopies of photographs of most of the family members represented in this accession.
  - Alden, Roger, 1796-1806 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burritt, Delphine R., 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cox, John Redeman, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Devereux, Catherine A. Johnson, 1832-1835 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dwight, Henry Edwin, 1823-1824 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hillhouse, Augustus, 1831-1847 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hoadley, George, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Houston, M., 1805 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Johnson [nee Bellamy], Anna Muirson, 1855-1856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Charles Frederick, 1827-1831 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    His personal letters from October 1830 to July 1831 include eyewitness reports and reflections on the aftermath of the French Revolution of 1830. He also invented the circular combination safe locks and the atmospheric docks for lifting vessels.
  - Johnson, Laura Winthrop, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Johnson, Robert Charles
    - Travel notes and letters on Europe during the Napoleonic wars, and essays on the history of ancient Rome and Italy, 1793-1830 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Travel diary that contains notes on the first French Revolution, the impact of the revolution on Italy, and the history of Rome, 1792-1793 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Johnson, Samuel William, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Contains correspondence with his brother, Robert Charles Johnson, with notes regarding the French Revolution.
  - Johnson, Sarah Dwight Woolsey, 1834-1839 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Johnson, William Samuel [estate management book], 1826-1832 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Verplanck, Elizabeth Johnson, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Woolsey, Cecil; Woolsey, John Mumford; Woolsey, Helen; Woolsey, Martha, 1863, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1828, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photocopies of photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Additional materials, 1795-1915; Accession 2005-M-107
  The accession is arranged alphabetically. It includes correspondence between members and friends of the Johnson family; journals of Johnson family members; and twelve sketch books of Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson. The sketches are in pencil and ink and were created on a trip to Europe and North Africa.
  - Bellamy, Anna Muirson Johnson [1839-1922], 1891-1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Berdan, David, 1826, [1867?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hermance, Agnes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Genealogy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Johnson, Charles Frederick [1804-(1882)], 1827-1849, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Johnson, Charles Frederick [1836-1931], 1904-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Johnson, Frances [1804-1882], 1833 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Johnson, Katharine Livingston Bayard [1845-1906]
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Quotations [possibly a journal], Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Record of books read, 1864-1868, 1887-1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Sketchbooks
      - [France], 1879-1893 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
      - [France, Morocco, and Gibraltar], 1898-1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-23)
  - Johnson, Robert Charles [1766-1806], 1795-1805, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Johnson, Sarah Dwight Woolsey [1805-1870; includes will and journal], 1823, undated
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Will, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Journals, 1823, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs of Johnson and Woolsey families, Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Woolsey, William Walton, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Additional materials, 1871-1886; Accession 2006-M-078
  - "Record of books read. No. 3" of Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson, 1871 September-1886 December (Box 1)
- Additional materials, 1869-1894; Accession 2007-M-048
  - Correspondence
    - Johnson, Katharine Livingston Bayard: letter regarding funeral of French President Carnot, 1894 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      The letter is a copy in sister Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy's handwriting.
    - Johnson, Sarah Dwight Woolsey: diary, 1869 August-1870 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Sister of Yale President Theodore Dwight Woolsey.
- Additional materials, 1833-1987; Accession 2008-M-074
  - Account books kept by Sarah Dwight Woolsey Johnson (1803-1870), 1864-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Johnson, Charles Frederick (1836-1931), to Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1898, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Johnson, Katharine Livingston Bayard, to sister Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1888, 1891-1900 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Johnson, Sarah Dwight Woolsey, to family members, 1833, 1841-1842, 1869-1870, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Johnson, Susanna Leverett Batcheller, to Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1900, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Johnson, William Woolsey, to sister Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1898-1918 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - "A Short History of the Woolsey Family for the Descendants of Theodore Salisbury Woolsey, Jr., and his Brother Heathcote Muirson Woolseyl", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notebook, written in French, of Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson, 1879, 1900, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes calling card and advertisement.
  - Poetry by Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1850, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional materials, Circa 1800s-1916; Accession 2009-M-078
  - Corrrespondence
    - Carmalt, Laura Woolsey Johnson, to Anna Muirson Johnson Bellamy, 1905-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Devereux, Catherine A. Johnson, to brother Charles Frederick Johnson, 1828 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes photocopy of "Journal of a Secesh Lady: The Diary of Catherine Ann Devereux Edmondston 1860-1866."
    - Devereux, Thomas P., to Charles Frederick Johnson, 1826, 1839, 1849, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Johnson, Charles Frederick, to daughter Anna Muirson Johnson, 1854 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Johnson, Sarah Dwight Woolsey, primarily letters to her husband, Charles Frederick Johnson, 1839-1868 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Document explaining settlement of debts owed by Samuel Wells, Circa 1800s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Possibly written by William Samuel Johnson, son of Samuel Johnson.
  - "Record of the Johnson Family", Circa 1800s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Believed to have been written by Katharine Livingston Bayard Johnson (1845-1906).
- Additional materials, 1785-2010; Accession 2013-M-011
  This accession consists of photographs, an account book, and genealogy.
  - Multi-generational account book, 1857-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Livingston family genealogy by Margaret S. Rutgers, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of eighteenth-century documents related to William Samuel Johnson, 1785-1798 (Box 1, Folder 3-14)
  - Photographs of New Haven, Yale University, and other Connecticut towns by Robert Bayard Severy, 2005-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)